<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A comforting farewel-word, to the Lords trembling-hearted peoples, at the removal of the cloud of His glory from the sanctuary, applyed as a present cordiall, against their heart-faintings.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5538A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52211992</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52211992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2742:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A comforting farewel-word, to the Lords trembling-hearted peoples, at the removal of the cloud of His glory from the sanctuary, applyed as a present cordiall, against their heart-faintings.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XVI, 22 --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A COMFORTING Farewel-Word, TO THE LORDS</hi> Trembling-Hearted People,<hi>AT THE Removal of the Cloud of his Glory from the Sanctuary, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed as a preſent Cordiall, againſt their heart ſaintings.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 22.</bibl>
               <p>We muſt thorow much tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation enter into the Kingdom of God.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 14. 7.</bibl>
               <p>It ſhall come to paſſe that at the evening time it ſhall be light.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 8. 6</bibl>
               <p>— If it be marvelous in the eyes of this People in theſe Dayes, ſhould it be alſo marvelous in mine eye ſaith the Lord of Hoſts?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Year,</hi> 1664.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:175595:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:175595:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHen the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> departed out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they met with many ſad difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in their way, before they entered into the land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> they had the Red Sea before them, the Armies of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> behind, and Rocks upon every hand, thus they were in very evil caſe, and when the Lord had manifeſted his power and goodneſs, in pathing a way for them on the face of the deeps, ſo that his Redeemed did walk thorow as upon dry land, even then, their troubles were not ended, for their faith had great tryals in the Wilderneſs, where they wandered fourty years; ſometimes fleeing before her enemies; ſometimes wanting Water, ſometimes hungry, ſometimes ſting'd with Serpents; yea, and that after they were at the very border of the land of Promiſe; ſo that they met with many afflicting diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations in their way, yea and at laſt there is a raging Jordan, when they are at the very entry into that Land wherein they were to reſt: And its very clear that <hi>Egypt</hi> was a Figure of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual bondage wherein we are by nature under the oppreſſion of the great Pharaoh Satan and ſin, whereunto even the Elect are ſervants before Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; and the place whereunto they went, <hi>viz. Canaan,</hi> which was a type of Heaven, whereunto
<pb facs="tcp:175595:3"/> Believers do go, and wherein they are to reſt; and therefore by the long weariſome journey thorow the waſt bowling Wilderneſs, and the many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties wherewith they did meet in their march to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> muſt ſhadow forth theſe many ſad and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting diſpenſations and diſappointments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Believers are exerciſe, from the day of their converſion from darkneſs to light, and from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Satan unto God, till the day of their paſſing from the miſeries of time, and entering into that glorious and bleſſed Reſt, that waiteth for the people of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. whereof <hi>Canaan</hi> was but a figure: And as toſſed <hi>Iſrael</hi> attained to that reſt thorow the goodneſs of God, ſending the pillar of the cloud to direct them by day, and the pillar of fire to lead them in the dark night, and inclining them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſame; ſo alſo ſhall Believers come to that bleſſed Reſt thorow the goodneſs of our God, who ſendeth theſe two precious pillars of his word and providence, (between which there is ſo ſweet a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and ſo pleaſant a harmony) to direct our way; <hi>Canaan</hi> is before us, therefore we ought not to be weary, though we be ſometimes walking in the deep and miry Clay, the reſt that is before us will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently make up all our loſſes and pains in walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither, therefore let us not give way to ſinkings of beart, which may occaſion wearying in the way, its good taking a view of the land that is afar off, that ſo by looking beyond the things that are ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing temporal unto the things that are not ſeen, being
<pb facs="tcp:175595:3"/> ſpiritual and eternal, we may eſteem our afflictions light and of ſhort continuance, being delighted with the forehand conceptions of that far more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eternal weight of glory, and may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged thereby to indure unto the end and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, &amp; ſurely there's good ground ſo to do, ſeeing that there can no ſader diſpenſation befall the Church, then that wch the cloud of witneſſes have travelled thorow, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. and we are commanded to walk by the foot ſteps of the flock in dayes of tribulation and aſtoniſhment, and it is moſt ſafe for us ſo to do, and to make our bleſſed Lord Jeſus our hiding place from the wind, ſtorm, rain and tempeſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 2. for he hath a real fellow feeling and ſimpathy with his people, and hath learned from his own bitter ſufferings to ſuccour them that are tempted, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 18. and alſo there is ſome comfortable diſpenſations alſo wherewith the Lord refreſheth weary <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there's a path thorow the Red Sea; there's a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Serpent to cure the ſtings of the fiery Serpent in the Deſart; there's an <hi>Elim</hi> as well as a <hi>Marah, Numb.</hi> 33. 9. where are twelve fountaines of Water, and threeſcore and ten Palm Trees, where weary Iſrael may be refreſhed, the Lord dealeth not with his people as if they were briers and thornes ranked in his way, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 4. but as with his Vineyard, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. contending in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure there, for removeing corrupt buddings forth; ſtaying his North wind in the day of his Eaſt wind, ſome breathings he giveth his people, ſome fair blinks
<pb facs="tcp:175595:4"/> after tempeſtuous ſtorms; ſo much the Scripture al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth his people to look for; and that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth doth tend ſomewhat to the encouragement of the Lords people to look for his goodneſs, as to this in the land of the living. Times and ſeaſons are known to our God, and we are only to look to his word as our rule, and to admit of no comfort nor comforter but is according unto this unerring rule, <hi>viz.</hi> the Scriptures. This Sermon going abroad thorow many hands, cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be ſo full as it hath been at the firſt, yet nothing is rendered here, but what was then delivered; there may alſo be found di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Erratas, and poſſibly ſome Tautologies which may be eaſily helped if the Author ſhall upon notice, or ſight hereof be perſwaded to reviſe it himſelf, in the mean time, let the Diſcreet Reader amend, or candidly paſſe over what he finds not ſo diſtinct, nor ſounding ſo well as in another caſe might be expected; Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175595:4"/>
            <head>A Comforting Farewell Word to the Lords Trembling Hearted People, at the removal of the Cloud of his Glory from the Sanctuary, as a preſent Cordial againſt their Heart-faintings.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Text JOHN. 16. 22.</bibl>
               <q>But I will ſee you again, and your Heart ſhall rejoyce.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OF all the people that are in the VVorld, the people of the Lord (who have dedicated and given away themſelves to him) have moſt, yea and only reaſons to be joyfull in their bleſſed King, and there are none that have ſolid ground of conſolation, but they alone; for albeit they have their times of heavineſs, when need requires, they, and only they, have alſo that which may hear up their ſpirits under the heavy preſſures of ſuch ſad and bitter Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations; and howbeit their lot may be to fit low for a time, and with the Church, <hi>Lamen.</hi> 1. 13. to interline this melancholious meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175595:5"/> among the reſt of their ſad Complaints; <hi>From above hath he ſent a fire into my bones, and it prevaileth againſt them; The yoak of my tranſgreſſions is bound by his hand; they are wreathed, and come up upon my neck; he hath made my ſtrength to fail, the Lord hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered me into their hands, from whom I am not able to riſe up!</hi> Yea although <hi>Zion ſhould be made to spread forth her hands,</hi> Ver. 17. and ſay, <hi>Now have I none to comfort me, for the Lord hath commanded concerning his people, that their enemies ſhould be round about them;</hi> Yet even then have they reaſon to rejoice in the Lord; yea, howbeit that alſo be enrolled amongſt their bitter Lamentations, which the Church hath, <hi>Lament.</hi> 2. 5. and <hi>Ver.</hi> 7, 8. where ſorrowful <hi>Zion</hi> bemoaneth thus; <hi>The Lord hath encreaſed in the Daughters of</hi> Judah <hi>mourning and lamentation, and hath violently taken away his Tabernacle, and made his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths to be forgotten in</hi> Zion, <hi>for he hath caſt off his Altar, and abhorred his Sanctuary;</hi> Yea, and howbeit ſhe concludes <hi>Ver.</hi> 8. That <hi>the Lord hath purpoſed in his heart, to deſtroy the wall, or, defence of the Daughter of</hi> Zion, <hi>having covered her with a cloud in his anger,</hi> Ver. 2. Which may cauſe pain in her inward parts, making her cry out as one that is far ſpent in a deadly Conſumption; <hi>Mine eyes fail with tears, my bones are troubled, my liver</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175595:5"/> 
               <hi>is powred out upon the Earth, for the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Daughter of my people:</hi> Yea though ſhe be neceſſitated, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. 9. to <hi>ſeek her bread with the peril of her life, becauſe of the ſword of the wilderneſs; And the Women and Maids are raviſhed in the Cities of</hi> Judah, Which is not one of the ſmalleſt miſeries ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying a lot of perſecution; Yea how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit <hi>Her Princes be hanged up by the hands of her Enemies,</hi> Chap. 5. 12. (So that it would ſeem that all hope were gone) yet among all theſe anxious perplexities, ſhe may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. 24. <hi>The Lord is my portion, ſaith my ſoul, therefore will I hope in him; For it is good that a man</hi> (even in ſuch a ſad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed condition) <hi>both hope, truſt, and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly wait for the ſalvation of his God;</hi> For though he be a little angry, and <hi>therefore cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth grief,</hi> Ver. 31, 32. <hi>Yet will he have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion according to the muititude of his mercies.</hi> It is fabled of a kind of Sea Creatures, that when the weather is fair, they weep, becauſe that after a blink there will be a ſtorm; but rejoyce when it is tempeſtuous, becauſe that after ſuch ſowr blaſts, there will be a fair day: I ſhall not ſay what truth is in this Fable, yet it hath a good morality to the people of God; For howbeit they may have <hi>a whole night of weeping,</hi> (though manifold afflictions) yet <hi>joy cometh to them in the morning;</hi> And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175595:6"/> they may carry out <hi>the precious ſeed of their ſupplications mourningly,</hi> yet ſhall they <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn rejoycing, bearing the precious ſheaves of the return of their ſupplications with them.</hi> So that they have reaſon, when among the moſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous and toſſing waves of manifold tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, to rejoyce; and have moſt ſolid ground of gladneſs of heart, even when their affliction is moſt bitter. We need no further proof of this, than the words which now we have read unto you. The Diſciples of Chriſt were in moſt ſad afflictions, and had great ſorrow of heart; and no wonder; for their dear Lord was to be taken from them, and ſlain; yet even in that non-ſuch condition of ſorrow, did the Lord propoſe this ground of encouragement to them. What ſadder and more bitter caſe could they be in than this? their dear Maſter was to be murthered and ſlain, and the hour was very near, which heightned their ſorrow and bitterneſs; yet the Lord doth encourage them againſt that non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuch affliction; <hi>Ye now therefore have ſorrow, but I will ſee you again, and your heart ſhall rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall give you a ſhort hint of the meaning of the words, and ſo draw forth the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars therein contained, whence we ſhall draw ſome points of Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Explication. Ye now therefore have ſorrow.</hi> This therefore hath a particular reference to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175595:6"/> what he had ſpoken concerning his approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufferings and departure; but eſpecially they are to be referred to <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. where he ſets down their condition by way of ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, taken from the ſore pains of a woman in Travail, when her hour is come, <hi>ſhe hath then more ſorrow and bitterneſs than formerly,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the hour of her Pains and ſore Labour is come; and this is your condition. I have told you that I am now ſhortly to ſuffer, and that this night I am to be taken from you, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this is the time wherein we muſt part, (my Caption and Death being near) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now ye have great ſorrow. Yet be not too Sore caſt down, and Diſconſolate, for,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will ſee you again:</hi> neither the Croſs, the Grave, the Tomb-ſtone laid upon me, the Guards and Bands of men, nor your Scatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and Baniſhment ſhall keep us at diſtance, we will meet again, for I'le riſe from the Dead, and we ſhall ſee one another, which ſhall bring great matter of joy unto you; <hi>your Heart ſhall rejoyce,</hi> your (now) diſcouraged hearts ſhall then dance and leap for joy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, <hi>When I ſhall ſee you again;</hi> your heart ſhall beat within you for joy and gladneſs when you ſhall ſee ſo unlike and ſo unprobable a Reſurrection, theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged fainting hearts of yours, ſhall then be ſwallowed up, and filled with exceeding
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175595:7"/> great, ſurprizing, overcoming, and uncredible joy. Now for the diviſion of the words, you ſee that the whole verſe contains, firſt the ſad caſe of Chriſts Diſciples, becauſe that now the hour was come wherein he was to be taken from them; in this phraſe, <hi>Ye now therefore have ſorrow.</hi> Secondly, there is <hi>the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Chriſt gives them againſt their Heart-fainting, and ſorrow of Soul, viz. <hi>the aſſurance of his return</hi> unto them, and the great joy of heart they then ſhould have, all which joy ye have in this phraſe<hi>—But I will ſee you again, and your Heart ſhall rejoye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVe had occaſion the laſt Lords day in another Congregation in this City, to ſpeak ſomewhat from the firſt part of the verſe, and entred alſo to ſpeak upon the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement given to them by Chriſt; and we ſhall not at preſent ſpeak of any thing which we then touched, ſave in ſo farr as may lead us to that which we are now to ſpeak unto you; and this being your preſent condition (with all the ſorrowfull people of God) we ſhall touch the ſame a little at preſent.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing we noted was from Chriſts diſtinct up-taking of their caſe, comparing it with verſe 5, 6. where they were ſo damped with ſorrow that they could not inquire where he was going, yet both there and here, he did take up their caſe diſtinctly, whence we obſerved.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175595:7"/>
            <p>1. <hi>Obſ. That Jeſus Chriſt is more diſtinct in taking up the perplexed condition of his diſcouraged people, than they themſelves can be.</hi> And this we noted, for the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of ſuch of the Lords people, as are often-times ſo filled with perplexities, that they neither know where to find themſelves, nor can make their ſad condition known unto others.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Obſ.</hi> Secondly, We noted from the ground of their ſorrow, which was Chriſts departure, <hi>That ſometimes the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt may leave and depart from his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as to the ſenſible enjoyment of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>Obſ.</hi> Thirdly, From the impreſſion of ſorrow was in their hearts at Chriſts departure, we obſerved, <hi>That there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo bitter to the ſpirits of the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as his withdrawment;</hi> Their hearts were filled with ſorrow. All theſe Particulars were ſpoken unto at ſome conſiderable length.</p>
            <p>And then, from the cauſe of the encreaſe of their ſorrow, which was the near approach of his departure (the hour was now come, and therefore they were filled with ſorrow) we obſerved, <hi>4ly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. <hi>Obſ. That the nearer the hour of Chriſts departure approacheth, the hearts of his friends are the more filled with ſorrow and bitterneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This we cleared from the frame and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175595:8"/> of the Apoſtles, <hi>their hearts were filled with ſorrow,</hi> as you ſee verſe 5. becauſe <hi>that now the hour was come that he was to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from them.</hi> From this point (when we had cleared it at length) we took occaſion to reprove three ſorts of people, making it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to our preſent condition.</p>
            <p>And firſt, from the point we reproved thoſe that are never troubled for any alterations can come upon the matters of God, although ſuch things fall out as prognoſticate Chriſts departure, yet are never moved, but will tell you, its all one whether Presbyterianiſm or Prelacie prevail, provided we be ſtill Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; and if changes and alterations come to a greater heighth, they will not trouble themſelves for that neither, but will tell you, it is all one whether Prelacie or Popery pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, provided we be ſtill Chriſtians; are not Papiſts Chriſtians? ſurely the Diſciples of the Lord were not ſuch, their heart was filled with more ſorrow as they ſaw the evidences of his going away. Ye ſee to what this Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has turned already, and therefore you that are indifferent people, when a ſhaking com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on the houſe of God (apprehending no danger, although theſe things prognoſticate Chriſts departure) the point tells you that you have reaſons to doubt whether you have any intereſt or part in the rich loading
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175595:8"/> which is in Chriſts ſhip of Goſpel Ordinances amongſt us, <hi>the nearer the time be of Chriſts departure, the more are the hearts of his people fill'd with ſorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly we reproved thoſe from the point, who though they pretend ſome intereſt in the rich loading of Chriſts Ship, and that their treaſure is therein, yet their hearts are not touched with the dreadfull evidences of Chriſts departure; they never change their chear, nor keep a rioband off their apparel for all the ſad evidences that are amongſt us of Chriſts departure, and going away, but are as proud, and as ſoon ſtirred up now to paſſion and anger, and are as vain as when there was not ſo dreadfull ſigns of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching departure; ſurely the point re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves ſuch.</p>
            <p>The third ſort reproveable from this point, were thoſe that are not only indifferent for all that is come on the work and people of God, as the evidences of Chriſts departure; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are debauching and drinking away their Spirits, not remembring the afflictions of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph:</hi> the Lords people are not ſuch, their hearts are ſorrowfull when they ſee Chriſt departing.</p>
            <p>The next uſe here was of Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to theſe who are now mourning for all the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> they are in their duty,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175595:9"/> and ſhall rejoyce with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when the Lord ſhall put on the beautifull garments of joy and praiſe upon her again.</p>
            <p>Then we came to the ſecond part of the Text, which is the Encouragement he gives them for holding up their fainting and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged hearts that were filled with ſorrow, becauſe of his approaching departure, in theſe words; <hi>But I will ſee you again, and your Heart ſhall rejoyce, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVherein firſt we noted his ſcope and aim, which was, to have their fainting Hearts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, for which cauſe he applyed this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Cordial. 2. There is the Cordial it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> the aſſured, and not to be doubted promiſe of his return. 3. The time when he did apply this Cordial, <hi>viz.</hi> when they were to meet with the Storm, and before they entred into the heat of the Furnace, which Cordial, or Encouragement, is drawn from that which afterward they were to receive, which was a joyous outgate. 4. There is the bleſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence and effect of this in this phraſe, and your Heart ſhall rejoyce. Laſtly, there is the firmneſs and ſtability of their conſolation and joy they would have at his return; <hi>Your joy ſhall no man take from you,</hi> though they clip the wings of your joy now, yet ſhall they not get it done at that day.</p>
            <p>From the firſt of theſe we obſerved,</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:175595:9"/>
            <p>5. <hi>Obſ. That whatſoever be the Perplexities of his peoples Spirits at his withdrawment, yet is it his deſire that they be comforted;</hi> this is his aim, while he tells them he will ſee them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and laſtly we left at this note from the Encouragement it ſelf.</p>
            <p>6. <hi>Obſ That no Storm can be ſo permanent or tempeſtuous, as that it can be able to keep the Lord and his people aſunder, he will ſee them again;</hi> this point we cleared from divers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, that in ſpite of the moſt ſwelling and tempeſtuous blaſts, he'l ſee or viſit his people again; from this point we drew firſt an uſe of reproof.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Uſe.</hi> To all thoſe who when the Church is low, turn their back upon her, as if Chriſt and She would never meet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; they evidence much Faithleſsneſs who do ſo.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Uſe.</hi> Secondly, we deduced from the point an uſe of Encouragement unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, applying it to the preſent diſtreſs now upon the Church: Chriſt is now going away, but if any would inquire <hi>what of the night,</hi> the anſwer is, as our night approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſo alſo the morning; Chriſt will ſee us again that dwell in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things we thought fit to name, this being your hour of ſorrow, becauſe of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175595:10"/> Chriſts approaching departure: But we ſhall dwell no longer at preſent upon what we then ſpake, but ſhall now come to that which we have further from the Lord to ſay unto you at preſent.</p>
            <p>And ſo now we come to another Doctrine from this Encouragement the Lord gives his Diſciples, <hi>Ye have ſorrow now becauſe the hour is come,</hi> but I give this unto you, to hold up your hearts againſt your preſent diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>I will ſee you again,</hi> Whence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. <hi>That the aſſurance of Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, is the only Cordial againſt the heart-faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the ſorrowfull Souls of his people at his departure.</hi> You ſee this point clear from the words, his Diſciples hearts were filled with ſorrow, and they had good reaſon ſo to be, they were to want their dear Maſter, who went ay between them and the ſtorm, and he gave them this, as the moſt choice and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſufficient Cordial, againſt their heart-faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>I will ſee on again,</hi> I am now to be taken away from you, I am within a little to be offered up, and my departure is at hand, (for <hi>Judas,</hi> that falſe hearted ſeeming friend, is gone away from me, and hath renounced his Miniſtry, as if he had been doing wrong all the time that he was following my Call and Order; and whereas he went from me alone,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175595:10"/> having no company (but my curſe, and an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil conſcience in his boſome) he is return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again with companies and troops at his back guarding him. But he is never a hair the honeſter man for all that he has gotten to back him, for he has betrayed me unto them, and has told them that he will profeſs kindneſs and friendſhip to me, till he get the black intent of his heart accompliſhed, yet he hath given them ſecret advice to hold me faſt, that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wen out of their gripes again) and your hearts are ſorrowful becauſe ye ſee the time draws near, and your hour is come; but I give unto you (my fainting friends) this choice Cordial, as ſufficient to revive and hold up your diſcouraged hearts, <hi>I will ſee you again.</hi> I ſhall propoſe ſome Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to make the truth of this Point appear: And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſ.</hi> 1. Firſt, It will be clear if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ground and cauſe of their ſorrow: for what was it that they were ſorrowful, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe he was going away? And the thing did moſt imbitter their ſpirits (as to this) was the near approach thereof, the hour was come wherein he was to be taken away from them; and if this had not been, they had not had this ſorrow of heart; for where there is no cauſe, there can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> effect: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts going <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> only cauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175595:11"/> of their ſorrow; his return again behoved to be moſt, yea ſufficiently encouraging, and ſo the aſſurance thereof the choiceſt Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al againſt the heart-faintings of ſorrowful ſouls at his departure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſ.</hi> 2. Secondly, It will be clear alſo, if we conſider, That his return evidenceth his being pacified towards his people. Ye know that his going away ſpeaks out much anger, and the moſt tender hearts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are moſt ſenſible thereof, and that it is not without great provocation he goes away, and are deeply affected therewith; and ſo muſt look upon his return as the cleareſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his being pacified towards them, and that his anger is turned away; and what can be ſo refreſhing as that? And therefore is there not ground to ſay, <hi>That the aſſurance of Chriſts return is the choiceſt and only Cordial againſt the heart-faintings of ſorrowful Souls at his departure?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſ.</hi> 3. Thirdly, The hope the people of God have of being freed of many great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and truſted with many choice bleſſings, when he returns, will clear this, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 9. 12. <hi>Yea and woe alſo unto them when I depart from them.</hi> He had ſpoken of many other miſeries, but he adds this as a non-ſuch and compleating miſery; <hi>Yea woe alſo unto them when I depart from them.</hi> And ſo it may be turned over
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175595:11"/> again (at his return) yea and all bleſſings unto them when I return unto them: and therefore in this reſpect the aſſurance of his return muſt be a ſufficient Cordial againſt the heart-faintings of the ſorrowful ſouls of his people at his withdrawment and going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. The firſt uſe here (as of Tryal, ſo alſo) is of Reproof to theſe who take not this choice and only Cordial now when Chriſt is going away: O what make ye your Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial? ye ſee the aſſurance of Chriſts return is the only and choice Cordial; therefore is this thy Cordial now, when the time of our Lords withdrawment is at hand, and the hour of his departure draweth near? what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you make your Cordial, yet well I know, that the thing which holds up and revives the ſainting hearts of his people, is the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his return and ſeeing us again.</p>
            <p>But more particularly I would ſpeak to two or three Cordials which ſome take unto themſelves at ſuch a time as this, which are none of Chriſts, but will prove poyſonous Pills in the end.</p>
            <p>The firſt poyſoning Cordial we name, is Self-quiet and preſervation; there are ſome who if they get preſervation to themſelves, it gives them Peace, and if they get any gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful place, it gives them yet more peace, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175595:12"/> quiets them, notwithſtanding their ſeeing Gods matters go wrong; O! is this thy Cordial? though thou ſeeſt the deſolation of <hi>Zion,</hi> and think'ſt her wronged, yet ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieſt and comfort'ſt thy heart with thy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment or Self-preſervation? O how dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Cordial is that, and how poyſoning a Pill will it prove!</p>
            <p>The ſecond Cordial is Self-hiding; there are ſome, who if they can couch down and hide themſelves, ſitting in ſilence, when God calls for a teſtimony at their hand, when all are Apoſtatizing from him: O how bitter a Pill will that prove in the end? and how well might that word be applyed to ſuch, which the Lord ſpake to another purpoſe, <hi>Micah</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Ariſe ye and depart?</hi> This ſhall not be your reſt, it ſhall caſt you out.</p>
            <p>The third woful Cordial that is very full of Poyſon, is Tipling and Drinking; there are ſome who acknowledge that Chriſt is getting wrong, and they have ſome ſort of heartleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereat, and yet draw not their encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement from the aſſurance of Chriſts return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, viſiting, and ſeeing us again, but go into the Inn to their 4 hours, and there drink up their hearts to a chearful frame. I am not ſpeaking here of thoſe abominable and miſerable wretches, who at their carrouſing at the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> will drink over
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175595:12"/> the ruine and deſtruction of the work and people of God in a cup of Wine; dreadful ſhall the doom and condemnation of theſe be from the Lord, their Judgment ſleeps not, and therefore we will not deal with them, but leave them to be taken ſevere courſe with to purpoſe, by the Lord, and to ſurfeit themſelves on their carnal delights, we leave them we ſay to the dreadful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of God, to take them in his own hand, with this certificate, that it ſhall be a wonder if ever the world ſee their repentance, for their doom is ſet down <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. where you ſee from the 9th v. They had broken down and builded up (at their pleaſure for ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening themſelves) without reſpect to the maker thereof, but they would not hear of their duty to God, for ver. 12. <hi>When the Lord God of hoſts called for faſting and weeping, to baldneſs and cloathing with ſackcloth, then behold joy and gladneſs, killing of oxen, ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſheep, eating of fleſh and drinking of Wine:</hi> but ſee with what contempt of Gods command in the mouth of his ſervants, did they thus glut themſelves with ſenſuality; <hi>Let us eat and drink for to morrow we ſhall die;</hi> the Prophets tell us we ſhould faſt and weep, what? ſhould we faſt and weep now, when we have made our ſelves ſtrong, and no arm can hurt us? when ſhould we feaſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175595:13"/> if not now? does the Prophet ſay that we ſhall die to morrow? then let us hold a hearty houſe to day, <hi>Let us eat and drink for to morrow we ſhall die:</hi> and as their ſin was deſperate, ſo alſo was their Judgment for their contempr; for the Prophet adds, <hi>It was revealed in mine eares by the Lord of Hoſts, Surely</hi> (or if I be to be truſted who am the unchangeable God) <hi>this iniquity</hi> (that is ſo preſumptuouſly committed) <hi>ſhall not be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from ye till ye die;</hi> and ſo he ſubſcribes their ſentence, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God of hoſts.</hi> So I ſay, there is ground to affirm, that it ſhall be a wonder if ever the world ſhall ſee your repentance, (if there be any ſuch here) &amp; ſo we leave you to the great &amp; dreadful God, to take you in his own hand, to take order with you to purpoſe. But the perſons I am ſpeaking againſt here, are your 4 hour Profeſſors, who would expect ſome part of comfort with the Church of God, when ſhe ſhall ſee you again, when he ſhall viſit <hi>Jacob</hi>'s tents, and have mercy upon his dwelling places: and yet take all their up-chearing at the Wine or Ale-houſe, and ſeek not this precious Cordial, the aſſurance of Chriſts return, to hold up their hearts. Oh, oh, is it a time for you to do ſo? if there be any ſuch here, I ſay unto you, believe it the ſtorm ſhall lay you by, and you ſhall not be invited to rejoyce with <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:175595:13"/> when Chriſt ſhall ſee her again, and ſhall give her the freſh ſweet milk of pure Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances again; for only they that mourn with her are invited to rejoyce with her, and they that (So) love her, will the Lord invite to ſuck (out of the breaſts of pure Goſpel-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances) the ſweet milk of Goſpel-conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherewith he feedeth and nouriſheth his children when he ſees them again; and no part of that Joy ſhall be unto you, but ye ſhall grow worſe and worſe, for thoſe that profit not by a tryal, they ſhall grow worſe, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Evil men (as well as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers) ſhall wax worſe and worſe;</hi> therefore all of you try your ſelves what Cordials you take, for the people of the Lords choiceſt Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial againſt their preſent heart-faintings, now at Chriſts departure, is the aſſurance of his return.</p>
            <div n="1" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>But I know ſome will be ready to object at this, and to ſay, there is no ground to think Chriſt is going away, and therefore what needs ſuch preſſing us to this only Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial? why may we not take our other encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſhall ſay firſt in anſwer to this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, I wiſh there were no ground to fear that Chriſt will go away: but I muſt alſo ſay, what heart can he have to ſtay amongſt us, and not retire himſelf (for a time) out of our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175595:14"/> ſight? And is not his glory already gone to the tops of the Mountains? howbeit we alſo hope that ſome of his dear children get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far-off-look of him from thence.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall ſpeak to four things that may ſpeak out his going away, and that he can have no heart to ſtay amongſt us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Evidence</hi> 1. The firſt evidence of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching departure is, the many Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his mind as to this, he hath ſent forth his faithful Miniſters, proclaming this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mountain of his viſible Church, they did foreſee this ſtroak, and lifted up their voice and cryed: and yet notwithſtanding their giving ſuch allarms of the Lords depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>(eſpecially ſince the dreadful ſtroak at Dunbar)</hi> O how ſmall hath the ſucceſs been? for though indeed many have been converted ſince that time, in mercy to their ſouls, yet O how little reviving hath been upon the hearts of Profeſſors? few have been ſtirred up to more ſeriouſneſs notwithſtanding all theſe allarms. It does not affright the hearts of many that Chriſt is going away, they think if he will go away, who can hold him? and if he will not ſtay, who can help it? hee'l take his own will, and ſo their moan is ended: and O how ſad is it that they will neither take hold of him to keep him, nor will they put on a mourning robe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175595:14"/> for him, and is there not ground then to fear his going away, ſeeing ſo few care for his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? and what heart can he have to ſtay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Evid.</hi> 2. The ſecond Evidence of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away is, our treacherous dealing with him, and our unfaithfulneſs to him, for, as a Wife treacherouſly departeth from her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſo have we departed from him; and have altogether loſt our credit at his hand, for neither Word, nor Write, nor Oath, nor Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant will bind us. And when he can neither believe the word that we ſpeak, nor the oath we ſwear, what expectation can he have of us, that we will be ſervants unto him? we did ſwear away our ſelves (to be a holy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto him) in our Covenant, and have we not broken our Covenant? and ſo ſaid (upon the matter) that we will not be a holy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo have loſt all credit at his hand, and what heart can he have to ſtay amongſt us? and is there not ground to fear his going away when he cannot believe the word that we ſpeak, nor the oath that we ſwear?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Evid.</hi> 3. The third evidence that we ſhall name that may give us ſad ground of fear that he will go away, is the tolleration of ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and all ſort of wickedneſs in the Land; and we need goe no farther than this the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther City of our Nation, which ſendeth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:175595:15"/> forth a dark ſmoak and cloud of profanity through all the Land. Theſe abominations take their beginning here, and doe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread and defile the whole Land. Our heart hath been like to bleed, when we have been ſitting in ſome Lodging Houſes by the way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide (as the Lord called us to be on our way) in ſome parts of the Land, where we heard numbers of Travellers, as they returned from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> ſinging over the moſt profane and ungodly Songs that could be deviſed, tending only to the ſtirring up of corruption in all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate and unmortified hearts who heard the ſame; and one of them ſaying to another, <hi>This is the moſt common or chiefeſt Song that is now in faſhion in</hi> Edenburgh, <hi>for, almoſt, there is no other Song to be heard in the Streets.</hi> This is a known truth, and would not ſuch abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, make Chriſtians ears abhor to hear them, or a ſanctified mind to record the ſame in memory, if neceſſity did not require, for reproving ſuch unfruitfull works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Ye know that this is no ſecret, for have not moſt of your own ears heard theſe profane Songs, on your Streets Nightly and Dayly, which is yet tollerated unto this day, and never curbed or puniſhed by theſe that are in Authority; which ſpeaks out great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency and want of zeal for our dear Lord Jeſus Chriſt? And O is it not ſad to ſee our
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175595:15"/> Mother City, wherein righteouſneſs did dwell, become ſuch a Mother of prophanity and ungodlineſs? And may not all this give us too ground to fear that our dear Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is like to goe away and leave us? And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide this, there hath been many other dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful abominations committed (by night and day) which would make Chriſtian ears abhor to hear, or tongues relate. O but this is not all, will you but hear a little farther, and we will tell you of a greater abomination than this, though little minded or laid to heart by many? and that is the turning over of this holy Book into Stage-playes! What is the holy Bible but the Eternal Gods Love-letter to his Church, wherein his mind is written? Yet is it turned over into Stage-playes: For will you but walk down to the <hi>Nether-Bow,</hi> and you ſhall there almoſt every night ſee ſome part thereof turn'd over into a Stage-play; is not this a horrid blaſphemy? Yet this is not done in a corner, they openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow the ſame; for while they ſtand at the <hi>Cloſe-head,</hi> calling in Paſſengers, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame their wickedneſs, ſaying, Walk in Gentlemen, walk in, and you ſhall ſee a choice piece of Art, and what is this choice piece of Art? You ſhall ſee <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve, Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> all walking in a lively manner, to ſee how they were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:175595:16"/> naked, and then deceived by the Serpent, and how <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew <hi>Abel:</hi> Oh, Oh, was it not this began all our miſeries and woes, did not this begin all our ſorrow and lamentation, and ſhall this be turned over into a Stage-play, and ſport, to make people laugh and be merry? O that ſome would cauſe plead for their Mother, that that order, might be taken with ſuch abominations. Theſe things we could not but mention, being ſo abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in the ſight of God. And may not this ſay, that he can have little heart to ſtay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, ſeeing we give ſo little eſteem of his bleſſed Word, that you ſee there is ground to fear his departure and going away from amongſt us?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Evid.</hi> 4. The fourth evidence of the Lords departure (which we ſhall name) is the corrupting of his Worſhip, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning the comly order of his Houſe in a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent way; the ſetting up a few vain ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeking men over the Inheritance of the Lord; who have (on the matter) renounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Miniſters, as not of God; And if ſuch men be fit for ruling the houſe of God, let the Bible and unbiaſſed people of God be Judge of the matter. This way was never bleſſed of God in our land formerly, as to the converſion of ſouls; and much leſs is it to be now expected that he will bleſs the ſame. O
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175595:16"/> how unbeſeeming a title would <hi>Paul</hi> have thought it for him, if any had come to him and called him, <hi>your Lordſhip,</hi> or, <hi>your Lordſhips grace!</hi> and how would he have abhorred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if he had ſeen Prelats Mytre upon his own head, and their ſyd robe upon him, and ſome bearing up his taile! no ground in the Bible for this; yet it is done. (let this neither he looked upon as matter of Laughter to ſtrangers, nor of affrightment to friends, being neceſſity conſtrains us to ſpeak of theſe things unto you.) Now may not all this give ſad ground of fear, that the Lord will go away and leave us, ſeeing ſuch abominations are ſet up amongſt us?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Now we would (in the next place) deſire you that are the people of God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage your ſelves in him: ye ſee (as we have cleared) <hi>That the aſſurance of Chriſts return, is the choice &amp; only ſufficient cordial againſt the heart faintings of the ſorrowful ſoules of his people at his departure:</hi> O therefore make uſe of this Cordial againſt the preſent diſtreſs and fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of your heart in this hour of affliction, becauſe of Chriſts departure; this is your preſent condition, your hearts are ſorrowful becauſe your dear Lord is now ſhortly to be taken from you; but let this hold up your hearts, <hi>He will ſee us again;</hi> therefore we ſay make uſe of this Cordial, for you that are his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175595:17"/> people have no leſs to hold up your fainting diſcoveraged hearts then his Diſciples got, and that is the aſſurance of his return; he will viſit our land, and ſo ſee us again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But ſome of the Lords affrighted trembling-hearted people will here object, alas that is the great thing in queſtion; and ye have ſpoken ſo much of his going away, that we can hardly think he will return to us again, and beſides all, he hath not tyed himſelf to any particular Church, and therefore no particular Church can apply this promiſe to themſelves, and ſo, what ground hath <hi>Scotland</hi> to apply this promiſe as a preſent cordial?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Though we have ſpoken much of his going, yet we have not ſaid that he will not come again; and we ſpoke to ſomethings the laſt day, for making it appear that he will come again.</p>
               <p>As firſt, our faithful Reformers Mr. <hi>Welſh,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wiſhart,</hi> Mr. <hi>Knox,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hamilton,</hi> &amp;c. others aſſerted that how be it Chriſt ſhall be crucified in <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet glorious ſhall his Reſurrection be; and may we not make uſe of this as a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial againſt our preſent heart-faintings?</p>
               <p>2. There are very many precious young men Students of Divinity whom the Lord hath fitted as poliſhed ſhafts for the work of the Goſpel, and of whom he hath never as yet made uſe therein; and ſhall we think that he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175595:17"/> will now lay them by, and not imploy them in his ſervice haveing been at great pains to fit them for the ſame.</p>
               <p>3. A faithful ſervice of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt who had this teſtimony, that he feared God, did lately amongſt us before many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes at his death openly declare his confidence as to this, That how be it our cloud may be long and dark, yet the Lord ſhall ſhine once more with the glorious light of his Goſpel upon theſe Lands, and ſhall we think that the Lord would have ſuffered his faithful ſervant to have brought himſelf under the imputation of a deceived Prophet at his death, being in ſo great a ſtrait for him, if he had not had a mind to fulfill his ſervants word in ſeeing us again?</p>
               <p>And we ſay now unto you, that the Lord had never more precious people in <hi>Scotland,</hi> then he hath now, (though there be many hypocrites,) neither hath ever had ſo many faithful Miniſters in a ſuffering time for ſerving in the work of the Goſpel as now he hath, though there be alſo many that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful; and we muſt think he will not lay them altogether byas uſeleſs, but rather that he hath work for them; and therefore we may take this as a ground of incouragement to confirme our hope of his ſeeing us again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="objection">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:175595:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2:</head>
               <p>But the Lord did caſt of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> when in a very flouriſhing condition, and did never viſit them again with the Goſpel; and why then may he not alſo go away from us, and never return nor ſee us again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There were never ſuch a formal mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage contract paſſed betwixt God and the ſeven Churches of Aſia, in their moſt flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition, as heath paſſed between God and <hi>Scotland;</hi> the Lord did formally and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marry our Land unto himſelf, in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage contract of our Covenant. <hi>Scotland</hi> hath this privilege beyond all the Nations or Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the World except the Jewes only; our Land is <hi>long ago</hi> a married land unto the Lord, and ſo there being a ſtanding marriage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract between God and our Land in our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, we moſt conclude that how be it he go away, yet he will ſee us again,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>But here it is, objected, our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was not ſo cleare a marriage contract, for we heard no audible voice from Heaven at the making of it, as <hi>Abraham</hi> heard at the making the Covenant with him, (for his ſeed) and therefore ſeeing we heard no voice, how ſhall we know whether he gave his conſent unto, or ſealed and ſubſcribed the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We anſwer how be it audible voices be ceaſed, yet muſt we conclude that God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:175595:18"/> ſpeaks as really now from Heaven as he did then, otherwiſe the Church were in a worſe condition now, then under the Law, which cannot be granted; therefore if he made it appear by his word and his providence; we moſt conclude that he did really ſubſcribe that marriage contract; and this we ſhall labour to make appear unto you.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that he gave his conſent unto, and ſubſcribed our Covenant as the marriage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract between him and our Land, will appear from the frame of great tenderneſs was upon the ſpirits of his people at the making of it, they were marrying away themſelves unto him, to be a holy people, and he did ſet home a lively frame of tenderneſs of ſpirit upon them (which is well known to theſe did ſee it) as a part of his ſealand ſubſcription to the marriage contract, and therefore we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that he did own it as the marriage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, and therefore that our Land is married unto him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, his ſubſcriping of the Covenant as the marriage contract between him and our Land, will appear from his after carriage to his Church, in that he did attend the ſame with bleſſed effects ſuitable to a ſtanding mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage relatfon; for when our Fathers had married away our Land unto him, he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to extend his husbandly care towards his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:175595:19"/> Church therein, and to do the duties becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a married husband; for after the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the marriage contract with our Land, he took up houſe therein, and began to beget Children by his new married Church, for holding up his family in our Land, for it's known that there were never ſo many conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and born again, as were after the making of that Covenant and Marriage contract, and have we not ground to take this, as his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to the Marriage contract, and his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal marrying our Land therein? and may not this aſſure us that he will ſee us again; ſeeing our Land is ſo formally and clearly marryed unto him, therefore make uſe of this your cordial againſt your heart-faintings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>But ſome affrighted heart will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and ſay, our Land hath rent the Marriage contract between God and us, and therefore we are no more a Married Land, having given up with God, and therefore have no ground <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> encourage our ſelves from the hope of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing us again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In anſwer to this, we altogether deny it to be in the power of any now to diſanull or make of none effect that Marriage contract; for it is with our Land, as with the bond ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants after the year of Jubile or releaſe; ye know that the bond ſervant under the Law, had his choice to ſtay with, or go away from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175595:19"/> his Maſter when the years of jubile came; but if the ſervant (having in his choice to go or ſtay) did ſay I deſire to ſerve my Maſter, for I am well with him, therefore I will not go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him, then he was brought unto the door poſt, and his ear was nailed thereunto, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which time, he had never liberty thereafter to go away from his Maſter, but behoved to ſerve him for ever; and if he did run away, then his Maſter (having a more laſting right in him then formerly) might purſue after him and bring him back again. So is it with our Land, our Fathers ſerved God a while, then the year of the Covenant was as the year of Jubile, for then it was put in our Lands choice to Covenant with (and marry themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) God, or not do it; and becauſe our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers found that it was good ſerving him, therefore they would not go away from him, nor continue free as they were, but entered into Covenant with him, to be his ſervants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ever, which was the nailing of our Lands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Lords poſt, and wherein we were tyed to him for ever: So that how be it our Land ſhould go away from him, yet now hath a mutual Covenant right in us, and may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and bring us back again unto him. And his ſubſcribing of the Covenant, as its <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,</hi> anſwereth all other doubts of mind, for our Fathers did not only Covenant and marry
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175595:20"/> themſelves away unto God, but alſo and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie as the repreſentative of his Church in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for it was an <hi>everlaſting Covenant, never to be forgotten;</hi> but that our Land ſhould remain a married Land for ever, and that from Generation to Generation, he ſhould have a Church and people therein, to ſerve him; and God did ſubſcribe this Marriage contract as everlaſting; for in evidence of his ſubſcribing that marriage contract both, as to the matter, and duration thereof, he did take up houſe in our Land, and did begin to extend his Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandly care towards his Church, in providing for her, and begeting Children by her which cleares that he did not only, ſubſcribe the Covenant, but alſo as it is everlaſting. So that it is not in the power of any now to make void or diſanull that contract when ſo perfected. Neither have the Lords people who are chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſted given their conſent to the riveing of the Marriage contract between God and our Land, it is againſt their heart, and how ridiculous a thing would it be thought by a husband, is his wifes friends who had formerly given their conſent unto, and ſubſcribed the Marriage contract) if they would come, after that he hath taken up houſe with her, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued with her in a married ſtate, and begotten Children by her (I ſay) if they would come and rive their double of the contract, and ſay
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175595:20"/> they would not have marriage to ſtand, would he ſtand to that? would he ſatisfie their deſire, and put away his wife (who deſires not to leave him) and ſcatter his family again, even after ſhe has brought forth children to him? ſurely not; he would rather cover her faults, as being more concerned in her, than her friends are, and would keep houſe with her: and ſuch indeed is the caſe betwixt God and <hi>Scotland,</hi> God hath taken up houſe with his Church in our Land, and therefore he will not ſatisfie her former friends deſire, in putting away his married wife, which is indeed the thing they aim at, for, though they ſay it is with ſomething in the contract they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied (as not drawn up according to their mind) yet indeed it is with the marriage that they are diſpleaſed, for their butt holineſs whereunto the marriage contract obligeth, and ſo the renting off their double of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract whereunto formerly they gave their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, will not make him give up with our Land, and ſcatter his family again.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it will be clear from the ſecond Pſalm, That the Lord will not give up with <hi>Scotland,</hi> for there you will find the preſent caſe of our Land clearly ſet down; for, there is plotting againſt the Lord and his anointed; and it is not with the Heathens only, that the Lord is expoſtulating, but alſo he is reproving
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175595:21"/> a people who have formerly profeſſed ſervice to him, and that have been under bonds and tyes unto him; for they ſay, <hi>Let us break their bands aſunder, and caſt their cords away from us;</hi> now if they had been Heathens, then had they been under no bonds to him as they were; yea, the phraſe is very emphatick, and very ſignificant, for they ſay, <hi>their bands,</hi> implying, that they would eſteem Gods bands to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the bands and cords of men that hurt them, therefore they ſay, <hi>their bands,</hi> whereas they ſhould ſay, <hi>his bands.</hi> And then the Lord begins to plead Chriſts right, and ſhews, that it is not by way of ſet tack for ſo many years, that Chriſt ſhould have theſe lands, but in poſſeſſion are they given unto him; for he ſaith, <hi>Ask of me, and I ſhall give thee the Heathen for thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion:</hi> Now it is concluded by all, that <hi>Scotland</hi> is the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt part, and corner of the world, and therefore it was given to Chriſt, and that not for a ſet time of lett, but as a ſure, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting poſſeſſion; ſo our Land being given to Chriſt, and that as an inheritance and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (whereof the ſecond Pſalm and 8. verſe is his ſtanding Charter in the Bible) we muſt not think that he will quit his poſſeſſion, but will keep his right and inheritance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we declare our Land a married Land
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175595:21"/> unto the Lord, and a ſure and on given unto Chriſt; and therefore, there being a ſtanding evidence and charter for his inheritance and poſſeſſion, and a ſtanding mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage contract, and the marriage relation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing betwixt him and our Land, he will not put away his married Church; no ſtorm ſhall take his poſſeſſion from him, nor be able to keep him away from his married Church, but in ſpite of all impediments he ſhall ſee us again. <hi>Smile O Heavens at this, and be Ioyful O Earth let all things break forth into ſinging before him! rejoyce greatly in the Lord, O our ſouls, and let all that is within us bleſs his holy name, let the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deemed of the Lord be joyful in their King, who hath married our Land unto himſelf, and given unto us</hi> (thereby) ſufficient ground for aſſurance of this, that he will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, and without all doubt, <hi>See us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So we come unto another Doctrine from the words, which is, from the time when he did thus comfort his Diſciples, <hi>viz.</hi> before they entred into the heat of the fernace. Whence obſerve,</p>
               <p>Obſ. 2. <hi>That before the Lord enters his people into a hot furnace of affliction, he uſeth to ſend them a comfortable word for incouraging their hearts in order to thoron-bearing, and a bleſſed</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:175595:22"/> 
                  <hi>out-gate.</hi> We ſee it clear in the words, ere they meet with the heat of the furnace, he tellls, he will ſee them again, and their hearts ſhall rejoyce: this is clear alſo from divers other Scriptures, before the Church go into captivity, he tells them, that at the end of 70 years they ſhould teturn again, and before his honeſt Prophet met with perſecution, from enemies, he told him, that he had made him <hi>an iron pillar and braſen walls againſt them, Jer.</hi> 2. 18. <hi>therefore though they would fight againſt him, yet they ſhould not prevaile againſt him.</hi> It was alſo the practice of the Apoſtles, to comfort the people of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Think it not ſtrange concerning the fiery trial, which is only to try, not to deſtroy you.</hi> Jam. chap. 1. 2. <hi>My brethren, count it all joy, when you fall into divers tentations.</hi> viz. in ſuffering, for they would get no hurt thereby, and fear, none of theſe things ſhall come upon thee, ſaith the Lord to his people, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. for though the Devil caſt ſome of you into priſon (yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it ſhall be well with thee) be faithful therefore to the death, and I ſhall give thee a crown of life; there is a ſad trial coming, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 10. but he ſends a comforting word to his people, <hi>Say ye to the righteous, it ſhall be well with him. Daniel</hi> 12. a ſad ſtorm, &amp;c. a time of trouble, ſuch as they never ſaw ſince a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and yet tells them, at that none ſuch ill
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175595:22"/> time deliverance ſhall come, and bleſſed ſhall they be that ſhall ſee the compleat delivery. So you ſee the point clear, viz. <hi>That the Lord uſeth to comfort his people e're he enter them into a hot furnace of affliction, or perſecution for his name.</hi> Many reaſons might be given, why the Lord does thus comfort his people e're they enter into a hot furnace for his ſake; but we ſhall not touch them here, but ſhall bring them in with ſome of the uſes for the ſaving of time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This lets us ſee what the bleſſed and tender diſpoſition of Chriſts heart is, who, before he enter his people in the heat of a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, will give them ſomething to refreſh, and bear up their hearts while in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Secondly, it lets us ſee, that it is the duty of Miniſters of the Goſpel (even of all that bear his name before his people) to comfort them when they are like to meet with a ſtormy trial for his ſake, they ſhould imitate their Lord and his Apoſtles, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted the Church in a day of trial, in the hope of a gracious out-gate. Therefore let us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort ſo many of you as are here, whom the Lord calls to ſpeak from his word unto his people, not only Miniſters, who have this great work lying on them, but alſo young men, (who muſt be faithful in the little, if ſo we may call it) labour to imitate your bleſſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175595:23"/> Maſter in this; ſee you a dark cloud coming upon the Church and people of God? O then comfort them againſt the preſent diſtreſs; tell them that they ſhall get a bleſſed out-gate, and that there ſhall be a bleſſed light after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent darkneſs. And I ſhall give you a few rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by way of motive, for incouraging you to comfort the people of God, to whom he ſends you to ſpeak in his name.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Motive.</hi> Firſt, comfort the people of God, for it is your duty, upon any hazard whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Say ye to the righteous, it ſhall be well with him, &amp;c.</hi> I command you ſpeak comfortably to them, though it ſhould coſt you never ſo dear; and may not this perſwade you to it, ſeeing it is his command? therefore ſet about it.</p>
               <p>2 <hi>Motive.</hi> You run a great hazard if you comfort them not, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Thou ſhalt hear the word at my mouth, and give them warning from me, when I ſay to the wicked thou ſhalt die, ſay thou ſo:</hi> (and ſurely ſpeaking freely againſt the wicked, makes much for the ſtrengthening of the godly) It may coſt you dear, your life may be in hazard for ſpeaking freely againſt them, and to comfort the godly. But if you do it not, their blood will I require at your hand.</p>
               <p>3 <hi>Mot.</hi> Comfort the people of God againſt the ſtorm, and you ſhall imitate your bleſſed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175595:23"/> Maſter who comforted his Diſciples when going away, with this, <hi>I will ſee you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4 <hi>Mot.</hi> If you do not comfort the people of God e're they enter in the furnace, it will be more difficult to get comfort born in upon them when their hearts are down, and they in the heat and bitterneſs of their affliction; their preſent ſorrow will not let them admit of comfort. Chriſt knew this well, for he ſaith, let theſe ſayings ſink down into your hearts, ground your comfort well now, elſe ye will be very incapable of hearing comfort, when I am taken from you and ſlain. And in the Text he comforted them, becauſe he knew they would not hear of comfort in the furnace: and may not this ſtir you up to this duty of comforting the Lords people now, e're they enter the furnace: that it will be a hard work to get them comforted when in the hot fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of affliction.</p>
               <p>5 <hi>Mot.</hi> Comfort the people of God e're they enter to the heat of the furnace; for ye know not if ye ſhall be near unto them when they ſhall have moſt need of comfort from you: if a perſecution for Chriſt did ſend away faithful Miniſters and their people into one ſhlp, when baniſhed, or to thruſt them into one priſon together, ye might ſuſpend your comforting them till you were ſent into ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175595:24"/> or priſon together: but the nature of a perſecution for Chriſt is, to ſmite the ſhepherd, and to ſcatter the flock: he is either thruſt into priſon, or baniſhed out of the land, or out of the world; and the flock is ſcattered, ſo that he cannot have opportunity to ſpeak comfortably unto them: and what trouble may he have in that caſe, if he hear of any thing falling wrong in them? if they faint in the furnance, his heart muſt challenge him for not comforting and ſtrengthening them when he had opportunity. And may not this encourage you to your duty? O therefore to your work while you have opportunity.</p>
               <p>6 <hi>Mot.</hi> O comfort the people of God, and ſtrengthen them for the ſtorm, and ye ſhall have great peace when taken from them. Chriſt had this to ſay, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>that he had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them his fathers word.</hi> And this was <hi>Paul</hi>'s great encouragement, in his laſt diſcourſe at <hi>Miletus, Acts</hi> 20. 26. <hi>that he had told them the whole counſel of God, and ſo was free from the blood of all men.</hi> O how great an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is this, when a godly Miniſter is thruſt from his charge, or is a dying, if he can ſay, <hi>now I am put away from my work,</hi> but bleſſed be God, I never withheld any thing from them, might tend to their encouragement or edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. There is not one ſentence in my mind that ever I refuſed to ſpeak, nor is there one
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175595:24"/> text of Scripture in my mind that the Lord bid me to preach from unto them, tending to their inſtruction or encouragement, that ever I refuſed to preach from, upon the greateſt hazard, and therefore I have no more ado; for my work is ended with my opportunity; as I am to have no more liberty to labour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, ſo alſo I have no more work to do, I laboured while I had opportunity, and ſo now my work and opportunity are ended at once: O how great peace may this give! and may not this incourage you to comfort the people of God e're they enter the heat of the Furnace.</p>
               <p>7. <hi>Mot.</hi> There ſhall not a hair of your head periſh for your faithfulneſs; they are all num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and your time is in Gods hand, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. the two Witneſſes cannot be killed, nor put from their work till they have finiſhed their Teſtitmony and prophecyed unto the end of the dayes appointed them of God: ye can neither be ſlain nor put from your worke as long as, blaſteth, though all the World ſhould oppoſe you; therefore with all peace and ſafety you may go about your work of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting the Godly, as being in his bleſſed hand who can preſerve his people though amongſt the midſt of adverſaries therefore encourage the people of God, for this your ſure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation while he has work for you is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:175595:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Is it ſo that the Lord Jeſus uſeth to ſend a word of comfort to his people e're he enter them into the furnace for his name, then they ſhould imbrace the ſame good word that is ſent unto them, though it be far off: I ſay they ſhould make uſe of the expectation of future comforts, for their preſent diſtreſs. You ſee Chriſt give, his people a promiſe, the ſweetneſs of which they were not to enjoy till after the ſtorm, yet he wills them to draw in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement from it for bearing up their fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and diſcouraged hearts; It was alſo <hi>Davids</hi> practicn, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. <hi>I had fainted, unleſs I had believed to ſee the goodneſs of the Lord, in the land of the living.</hi> It was but a far of look of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my faith got, all that I could come at was the hope of ſeeing his goodneſs in the land of the Living, once e're I ſhould go off this World; yet though it was far of, I was glad to grip to it, I durſt not put it away, but laid hold on it, and ſo incouraged my ſelf by it, againſt my preſent faintings of heart: Therefore we ſay unto you that are here, you ſee this is your duty to comfort your ſelves in the expectation of future conſolation, yea it is for this very end that Chriſts ſends it: O therefore make it practicall, when God ſends a word of conſolation unto you, cloſe with it for your comfort; it is your duty ſo to do eſpecially when it it is conveyed to you with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:175595:25"/> danger &amp; hazard, and ſo I ſhall ſay no more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, but leave it on you, for you will have enough to do with all your comfort (far off, or near) to you when ye meet with the ſtorme, therefore let not a word fall to the ground when he ſends it for yout comfort. I come to the laſt, note which is the bleſſed effect ſhould flow unto them upon his return, which is joy of heart, <hi>I will ſee you again, and your heart ſhall rejoyce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ. That the time of our Lord Jeſus return, after ſnell and ſtormy blaſts, is the moſt joyfull and dancing dayes of his people.</hi> This we find clear from many Scriptures, when this glorious Sun ſhineth after a dark Ecclipſe in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Church, all the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Zion are made to rejoyce, and no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for ſhe hath many bruiſes, and he comes with healing under hir Wings: And in the text, ye have now ſorrow, but I will ſee you again, and your hearts ſhall rejoyce. We ſhall give you ſome Scripture conſiderations to cleare the point a little further, paſſing by what we ſaid formerly as to their ſeeing him pacified when he returns; whereas his going away prognoſticates anger, and as to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freed of much miſery for his going away, is the moſt cronning miſery, Wo alſo unto them when I depart from them, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> and ſo it may be turned over, yea, and all bleſſings
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175595:26"/> unto them when I return unto them, which muſt make them as joyful dayes, but further the point will be clear if ye conſider.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſ.</hi> 1. Conſider firſt her geting on her new apparel, Zion hath her mourning garments in mourning dayes when ſhe lyes in the duſt; O but when the Lord returns again unto her, ſhe gets on Garments of Gladneſs: ſhake thy ſelf from the duſt O Zion, and put on thy beautiful Garments O Jeruſalem, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52. 1, 2. &amp; therefore ſeeing ſhe gets on brave Apparel, muſt ſhe not be made very glad, and ſo have not reaſon in this reſpect to ſay that the time of Chriſts return after ſuch blaſts, is the joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dayes of his people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſ.</hi> 2. Oftentimes Zion gets the intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her pardon ere ſhe come out of the Furnace. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 2. <hi>Tell her that her iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are pardoned.</hi> And therefore in this reſpect the time of Chriſts returning muſt be the moſt joyous dayes to his people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſ.</hi> 3. Zious ſtouteſt enemies (who ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her down in the dayes of her affliction) are made to ſubmit themſelves to her, when the Lord <hi>ſees her again. Iſai.</hi> 60. 14. <hi>The Sons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of them that afflicted thee ſhall come bending unto thee, and all they that deſpiſed thee ſhall bow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves down at the ſoles of thy feet, and ſhall call thee, the City of the Lord, the Zion of the holy oue of Iſrael.</hi> Though they repreached you in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:175595:26"/> the day of your low condition, yet they ſhall be forced to acknowledge you to be my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when they ſhall ſee my goodneſs to you at my ſeeing you again; muſt not that be very comfortable to the people of God, when they ſee thoſe who formerly in their affliction domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neered over them, treading on their necks, coming and ſubmitting themſelves unto them, and confeſſing them (whom formerly they perſecuted) to be the Lords people, and ſo there is ground in this reſpect to ſay, that the time of the Lords returning, after cold and ſtormy blaſts, is the joyous and dancing days of his people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſ.</hi> 4. Conſider 4. when the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns for delivering his people, he both ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize them with unexpected deliverance, and alſo maketh much of his glory ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. 126 <hi>Pſal. When the Lord brought back our captivity, we were like them that dream,</hi> we were ſo amazed with ſuch an unexpected de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, that we were like folks ſpeaking in their ſleep for joy; then was our mouth filled with laughter, and ſo our dancing dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. 16. When the Lord builds up Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he appears in his glory, he maketh the bright rayes of his glory glance upon his Church, making it evident that he regards the prayer of the deſtitute, which formerly he ſeemed to deſpiſe (howbeit he did
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175595:27"/> not ſo indeed) and ſo ſetteth their hearts a dancing again.</p>
               <p>Conſider 5. Zion hath then her ſpring time of flouriſhing; and heareth his moſt ſweet voice, and is invited to communion with him, of whom ſhe could not get a blink formerly, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Ariſe my love, my fair one, and come away, for the winter is paſt,</hi> wrath and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is now departed, <hi>the rain is over and gone;</hi> thy ſtormy dayes are by thy hand; <hi>and the flowers appear on the earth, and the time of the ſinging of birds is come.</hi> Heartleſs Zion muſt now have her Songs again, for the winter is over, <hi>the fig-tree puts forth her young figs, and the vines with their tender grapes give a good ſmell;</hi> there is a brave ſpring time of all Zions graces, and the ſweet ſmelling of her oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>when the Lord</hi> (of whom ſhe had been deſerted) <hi>ſees her again:</hi> and ſo have we not reaſon in all theſe reſpects to ſay, <hi>that the time of the Lords returning, is the joyous and dancing dayes of his people.</hi> But while we are ſpeaking of the joyous, dancing, and merry dayes the people of God have when he ſees them again, we would give you advertiſement, that the point whereupon we are, is a large and noble diſh of the glorious marriage feaſt of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and therefore before we go any further to make application hereof, <hi>we do, in the name, and by the authority of our dreadful Lord and</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:175595:27"/> 
                  <hi>Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, excommunicate and debarre from this bleſſed part of the Goſpel feaſt,</hi> firſt, <hi>all thoſe that have been active in carrying on our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ctions from God, and his way, that they take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut upon them to meddle with this joy the people of God ſhall have at his return, being ſtrangers to all the toyl his people are put unto, in labouring to keep their garments clean.</hi> Secondly, <hi>we do excommunicate from this bleſſed part of the Goſpel feaſt, all caſters off of the yoke of God in the holy band of our Covenant.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>all thoſe that have not heart-ſympathy with Zion in this day of her low condition: fourthly, We do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate and debarr from this part of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Feaſt all thoſe in whoſe heart it is at preſent to do any thing to the hightening of the affliction of any of the people of God, in relation to his new controverted but glorious work in this preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, whether by falſe accuſation of them, or falſe witneſs bearing againſt them; ſurely ſuch ſhall not taſt of this bleſſed part of the marriage ſupper and Goſpel feaſt. fifthly,</hi> All thoſe who are not willing to adventure their whole Eſtate, I and, Life and Geir, in the ſame broken Ship with Zion, to die and live, ſink and ſwim with her in all her afflictions, and all ſuch as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the greateſt hazards, will not (as they are called in their ſtations) do all way tend to her inſtruction and incouragement. And laſtly we excommunicate and debar from this noble diſh
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:175595:28"/> of the Goſpel feaſt, <hi>(viz.</hi> the joy the Lords people have at his return) all ſuch as willingly (without remorſe or endeavour to amend) are wallowing in the ſame ſins wherein they did lie before the Lord began to ſmite us; eſpeci-O you four hours profeſſers, who think ye love Zion, and do approve the things that are beſt, yet are not leaving off your four hour-companions; be it known to all of you whom we have named, it is not for your ſakes that our Lord Jeſus will ſee or viſit us again, wherefore we ſay unto all of you, keep your hands from off the precious bread, which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the mourning and heavy hearted ſons and daughters of Zion; for only they ſhare with Zion in her conſolations, when the Lords ſees her again; who, ſo loved her, and mourned for her, in her low condition, and without the Wedding garment of repentance for theſe evils, and a forſakeing of them, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a heart and practical ſympathy with Zion in this her diſtreſs, you ſhall never taſt of this choice part of the Marriage ſupper, and Goſpel feaſt, wherewith the fainting and trembling diſcouraged hearts of the people of God ſhall be cheared up and revived, when he ſees us again; but we deſire not altogether to leave you here, and therefore we ſay if ye will be ſo wiſe for yout ſelves, as to joyn your ſelves to Zion, and from a principle of heart
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:175595:28"/> honeſty, take a ſhare of a ſuffering lot with her, you ſhall be very welcome, and upon theſe terms we heartily invite you to come and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of theſe dainties; otherwayes you cannot be admitted; for none can rejoyce with the people of God, but they who mourn with them, none can land with them upon the ſhore of conſolation with them ſave they who ſet their face to the ſtormy and tempeſtuous waves, ſwimming thorough the deep flouds of perſecution and affliction with them: But upon the other hand we do in the bleſſed name, and authority of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily invite you to this bleſſed Feaſt of joy, who are the fainting and ſad hearted people of God; we are not ſpeaking to you of the great conſolation wherewith your ſouls ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, when our Lord ſees us again; draw near therefore O ye diſcouraged ſons and daughters of Zion, eat of this fat, and drink of this ſweet, for only to you doth this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed feaſt belong, and unto you and you only is the word <hi>of this conſolation</hi> ſent; O rejoyce in the hope of what dancing dayes you ſhall have, when Chriſt ſees us again, which joy ſhall then wreath a neceſſity of gladneſs of heart upon you, as a Chain about your neck; draw near therefore with all humble bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and chearful confidence unto this feaſt of joy; <hi>Eat O friends, drink abundantly O beloved,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:175595:29"/> 
                  <hi>feed largely, eat and drink for the time to come, and journey that is before you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for further application, may not all we have ſaid make it appear that the people of God as to their ſtate are a moſt bleſſed people? and may not all we have ſaid be ſufficient for engaging the hearts of you that are as yet ſtrangers to the firſt dancings of a glorious work upon your hearts, to come and joyn your ſelves to Zion, to take a life and death with the people of God, ſeeing they have that which may bear them up in the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt afflictions, and moſt tempeſtuous fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> wherein they may be toſſed?</p>
               <p>But (that we may draw to a cloſe) we would now ſpeak a word unto you the people of God, as to your preſent duty from all we have ſaid, ye ſee we have cleared this good ground to hope that our Lord will ſee you again, and that ye ſhall have very joyfull and dancing dayes when that ſhall be, for <hi>your hearts ſhall rejoyce;</hi> O therefore <hi>bleſſed hearts,</hi> be comforted (in him) in the hope and ſure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of this precious day; let us in the hope hereof reſolve chearfully to ſet about thoſe duties ſuitable to us in order to his ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us again, let us reſolve to be faithful unto him in his abſence; let us reſolve in the ſtrength of him to bide by his precious truths and intereſts, let us keep our ſelves free from
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:175595:29"/> touching the unclean thing, for this will haſten his ſeeing us again, let us do all things that tend to the good of his cauſe, that the cauſe of our Lord Jeſus may win the day, though we ſhould fall in the field of ſuffering; guard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all pollutions of his Ordinances; keep cloſe by the covenant whereof ye need not be aſhamed, for it binds you to nothing, but holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards God, and Loyalty towards your Prince, and ſo is the moſt clear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eanly and ſure Oath of Allegiance under Heaven; yea, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Marriage contract between God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Land, ſo ye need think no ſhame of any thing in it, but may caſt up your face before all the World, owning and avowing it before Heaven and Earth, Angels and Men; in a word let us ſet our face as flint againſt the ſtorm, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving upon the greateſt of hazards in the Lords ſtrength not to yield to any thing not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the word of God, when matters are violently carried on againſt Jeſus Chriſt, his intereſts and people, it is the duty of all the faithful ſeed to ſet their face as flint againſt the ſtorm, and not to yield in a foot to any thing preſt upon them contrary to his word. Now 1. here is your work, be faithful unto him, bide by the truths of him, who endured the Croſs for you; defile not your ſelves with abominations preſt upon you. 2. The ſimpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and fellow feeling of our great high Prieſt,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:175595:30"/> who is touched with the feelings of all our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, together with the precious promiſes is your expence and charges, whereupon you are to ſpend on your way. 3. Chriſts ſeeing you again, together with the joyful and dance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayes ye ſhall then have, is your incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; O therefore up with your fainting and diſcouraged hearts, for nothing ſhall keep him away from you! he will ſee you again, and your heart ſhall rejoyce! ſometimes he has even returned to theſe places where they had formerly ſought to ſlay him; <hi>What</hi> (ſaid his Diſciples) <hi>wilt thou go up to Jeruſalem, knoweſt thou not that not long ago the Jewes ſought to ſtone thee, Joh.</hi> 11. 8. Yet he went, and ſo will he return again to us, he will give us a gracious viſit, and our hearts ſhall rejoyce, but many others ſhall look very blank at that day when he ſees us again; but your heart ſhall revive at that day: O therefore comfort your fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hearts in the hope of it, that ye may go chearfully through the preſent diſtreſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the keeping of your ſouls unto him, in the way of duty and well doing, as into the hands of a faithful Creator, who will make a glorious accompt of all that is committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. <hi>Now we have told you that our Land is a married land, and that therefore he will ſee us again, and we call God to record upon our ſoules that he laid a neceſſity of ſpeaking this unto you,</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:175595:30"/> 
                  <hi>and that under no leſs hazard then of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected of him, never to be countenanced in his work again, but to be made a weathered ſpectacle of his diſpleaſure, for diſobedience, durſt we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſay theſe things unto you, and we are ſure it is from the Lord unto you.</hi> And receiving his tender hearted Chriſtian friends trembling, which he ſuppoſing might be for fear of his danger he ſpeaks theſe words, <hi>What ayleth you, O faithful friends in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt? and why does your faces look pale? are ye affraid of the approaching ſtorm, O may not this quiet your hearts that he will carry you well through, will ſee you again, and cauſe your hearts rejoyce.</hi> Why then are ye diſconſolate, are ye affraid to loſe a friend for Chriſt and his cauſe? O may not this ſatisfie your hearts as to this, that it is not loſt which Chriſt getteth, it falls in a friends hand. Secondly, We ſay unto you that there is protection and ſecurity in our God, in the moſt tempeſtuous and ſtormy day; <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26. 2. <hi>We have a ſtrong City</hi> (what is the City there? it's Gods ſalvation) <hi>ſalvation will God appoint for walls and bulwarks.</hi> where ye may ſee that when the Lords people have no outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, neither walls nor bulwarks, then the Lords Salvation is walls and bulwarks for their protection and ſhelter, ſo that he can ſhelter them as within ſtrong holds, even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they are amongſt the greateſt of ſnares:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:175595:31"/> and ſo may not this quiet your hearts that the Lord can protect your friends though in the midſt of trouble; and you have this to make up all your loſſes,—our Lord Jeſus will ſee you again: we leave you with the ſame ſoul comforting promiſe in your boſome, that howbeit now you have ſorrow, becauſe your hour is come yet he ſhall certainly and without all doubt ſee you again, and your heart ſhall rejoyce, and ſhall add no more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but unto him that is able to perſwade your Hearts of this, <hi>That he will ſee you again;</hi> and who can manifeſt the ſame in your joyfull experience we deſire to give Praiſe. The end of the firſt Sermon.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
